Finding Aid for Isaac Newton Demmon papers, 1858-1920
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Isaac Newton Demmon papers 1858-1920
Demmon, Isaac Newton, 1842-1920.
1 linear foot and 1 oversize folder
851193 Aa 2; UAm
Professor of English at University of Michigan. Correspondence, essays, a diary, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was gathered from various sources, including a transfer from the estate of Professor Demmon (donor no. 1294 ); from the Demon family (donor no. 2820 ), and from the Graduate Library of the University of Michigan (donor no. 1278 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Isaac N. Demmon was born in Northfield, Ohio on August 19, 1842. He attended Butler College in Indianapolis for two years, then left to enlist as a private in the 132nd Indiana Infantry in the Civil war. In 1865 he entered the University of Michigan, graduating in 1868 (B.A.) and 1871 (A.M.).
Upon his graduation in 1868 Demmon was appointed professor of Greek in Alliance College, Ohio. Two years later he resigned to accept the chair of ancient languages in Hiram College. In 1872 he became an instructor in mathematics at the University of Michigan, resigning shortly to become principal of the Ann Arbor High school. In 1876 he returned to the university as assistant professor of rhetoric and history. In 1881 he was appointed to the chair of rhetoric and English, and when that chair was divided in 1903, he chose the chair of English.
Demmons was instrumental in the development of the university's library. He was an expert bibliographer and was made curator of rare books at the university. It was because of his persistence and relationship with Michigan Senator James McMillan that the library received McMillan's collection of Shakespearian books. Demmon retired from the university in February 1920. He died September 29, 1920.
The Demmon collection is comprised of the following series: Correspondence; Manuscripts; Essays and addresses; Other papers; and Photographs. The correspondence is both professional exchanges and personal letters among family members. Included are Demmon's student letters from Butler University and The University of Michigan, and two Civil War letters (1864) written while he was serving with 132nd Indiana Infantry. Among his professional correspondence are letters from James B. Angell, William L. Clements, Martin L. D'Ooge, Karl E. Guthe, Henry B. Joy, James McMillan, Moses C. Tyler. There are also lecture notes and other papers pertaining to his teaching duties; three volumes of personal accounts (1899-1920); a diary (1869) kept while he was a professor at Alliance College, Ohio, in which he mentions Mark Twain and John A. Bingham. The photographs include portraits, family photos and tintypes; photos of Demmon in the classroom, and of Demmon's residence in Ann Arbor.
Subjects:
Alliance College.; Butler University.; Hiram College.; Hoyt Public Library (Saginaw, Mich.); United States. Army. Indiana Infantry Regiment, 132nd (1864); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.; University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan--Students--Correspondence.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Demmon family.; Demmon House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Demmon, Isaac Newton, 1842-1920.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Living rooms.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934; D'Ooge, Martin Luther, 1839-1915.; Guthe, Karl Eugen, 1866-1915.; Hinsdale, B. A. (Burke Aaron), 1837-1900.; Joy, James F. (James Frederick), 1810-1896.; McMillan, James, 1838-1902.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.
Genre Terms:
Daguerreotypes.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Correspondence
  - General, 1858-1920 and undated, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Emma to Isaac, 1867-1881, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Isaac to Emma, 1871-1872 (Box 1)
  - To Emma Regal Demmon, 1862-1903 and undated, 6 folders (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Goldsmith and Sheridan (Box 1)
  - Religious Poems of the Nineteenth Century (Box 1)
- Essays and Addresses
  - Trip to England (Box 1)
  - Chaucer and his Age (Box 1)
  - The Place and Limits of Formal Rhetoric in the Preparatory School, 1895 (Box 1)
  - Pythonian Society addresses, 1864-1865 (Box 1)
  - M.L. D'Ooge memorial (Box 1)
- Other papers
  - Lecture notes on course taken in aesthetics (Box 1)
  - Hoyt Public Library, and booksellers materials (Box 1)
  - Receipts and business papers (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (include brief biographical sketch of Ridgley Powers) (Box 1)
  - Account books, 1899-1920, 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1869 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  (see also oversize folder UAm)
  - Portraits (Box 1)
  - Family (Box 1)
  - Demmon in classroom (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor home (Box 1)
  - Family members (tintypes) (Box 1)
  - Daguerreotypes (unidentified) (Box 1)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.
July 1887, June 23, 1902, Jan. 7, 1904, Nov. 1905, Aug. 21, 1907
Atwood, Meranda (cousin of IND)
1860: description of central California; tells of efforts to get escaping slave into Canada; also comments on Lincoln
Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.
Nov and Dec. 1914
Demmon, Levi
April 17, 1865: tells of preaching funeral sermon for Lincoln
Flemming, E.
Oct. 13, 1866: letter concerns politics, support for Stevens, political corruption in his home (Indiana) district
Guthe, Karl Eugen, 1866-1915.
Sept-Oct. 1914
Heineman, David Emil, 1865-1935.
Throughout, 1881-1911
Joy, James F. (James Frederick), 1810-1896.
Dec. 4, 1882
McMillan, James, 1838-1902.
Jan. 6, 1897, Jan. 27, 1897
Magill, J. C.
March 29, 1872 with mention of Chicago after the fire
Van Dyke, Henry
Nov. 14, 1905 re Demmon's editing "As You Like It"